Okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*.
Today's דף *Daf* is דף ה׳ *Daf Heh*. And we're going to
see today, like some of the previous דפים *Dappim*, not only is
this פרק *Perek* much shorter because of the ר״ן *Ran*, but also
there are, as of right now, we're not really dealing with like
dense סוגיות *Sugyot* as we've been dealing with. So let's see. They
should go pretty quickly because we're still trying to figure out, we're
working out this statement of שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*. Now שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*
said that the משנה mishna *Mishnah* was obscure. Okay, so the משנה
mishna *Mishnah* said like if someone says מודרני ממך mudrani mimcha, *Mudrani
Mimcha*, מופרשני ממך mimcha, *Mufrehani Mimcha*, שאוכל לך lecha *She'ochal Lcha*, שאטעום
לך lecha *She'at'oam Lcha*, so that works and that's a יד yad
*Yad*. Okay, and the question of how to read that משנה mishna...
*Mishnah* is, does that statement only work and that statement only work,
which is how it sounds like, or שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* is choosing
to read the משנה mishna. *Mishnah* that no, no, you need both
of them together. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* went and proved
you don't need both of them together, each one alone actually works.
Okay, so שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*'s position has been modified to say that
no, no, if you just say מודרני ממך mudrani mimcha, *Mudrani Mimcha*,
which is very broad and generic, it means in both directions. We're
separating from you, I'm separating from you,
and that basically means that I am forbidding not only your stuff
on me, but my stuff on you. It works in both directions.
Only when you say שאוכל לך lecha *She'ochal Lcha*, those things of
yours that I will eat of yours, okay, it's just as it
takes for the predicate, then only then it means your stuff is
forbidden to me, but not in the reverse. But without this qualifier,
it means in both directions. That's how we're interpreting שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*'s
statement. Let's take a look now where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes
with that. Okay, you know what? Let's pick that up. Let's reread
that from three lines from the bottom on דף א׳ ע״ב *Daf
Aleph-Beis* just to give us context. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
אלא אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel, *Ella Amar Shmuel*, שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* says
point that he added that qualifier, הוא דאסור hu de'assur. לחבירו ומותר
*Hu De’assir Lcha’veiro Umutar*. That's why you're saying these things of yours
that I would eat of yours are forbidden to me, in that
direction. אבל *Aval*, top of דף א׳ *Daf Aleph*, אבל אמר מודרני
הימך Mudrani hemcha, *Aval Amar Mudrani Himcha*, I am sort of separating
from you, לחודיה *Lchudei* by itself, שניהם אסורים shneihem assurim, *Shneihem Assurin*,
both are forbidden because it works in both directions. כי הא דאמר
רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yossi bar Chanina *Ki Ha De’amar Rabi
Yose Bar Chanina*, מודרני Mudrani הימך שניהם אסורים shneihem assurim, *Mudrani Himcha
Shneihem Assurin*. If I say I am separated from you, then they
are both forbidden. Now we're going to try to see is that
really true that when you make a statement like that it's interpreted
in both directions?
Yes, I didn't notice this. What is this word הימך *Himcha*?
That means like ממך mimcha, *Mimcha*? I don't know, yeah, I don't
know. Do I ask for one person? No,
I don't know the exact grammar, but it means ממך mimcha *Mimcha*.
Okay? Like
ממנו *Mimmenu* is from him, right? So ולא כל הימנו *Vlo Chol
Himmenu*, whatever. So הימך *Himcha* means from you. But הימנו *Himmenu* is
also a form of ממנו *Mimmenu*, right? So I don't know. It's
some
Aramaic variation of it. I don't know anything else.
What is הימנו *Himmenu*? I can't think of it out
of the context, but yeah, okay.
To make it more confusing, Steinsaltz vowelizes it as הימך *Himach*. הימך
*Himach*?
Yeah, okay. הימך *Himach*, הימך *Himcha*. Okay, more Aramaic. All right, enough
grammar. Okay, back to business. כי הא דאמר
רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yossi bar Chanina *Ki Ha De’amar Rabi
Yose Bar Chanina*, and everybody's favorite class from school, grammar. כי הא
דאמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yossi bar Chanina *Ki Ha De’amar
Rabi Yose Bar Chanina*, מודרני Mudrani, הימך שניהם אסורים Sheneihem asurim *Mudrani
Himcha Shneihem Assurin*. תנן *Tnan*, the משנה mishna *Mishnah* says הריני עליך
חרם hareini alecha cherem *Hareini Alecha Cherem*. Behold, I am on you
חרם cherem, *Cherem*, which we said means my property, חרם cherem. *Cherem*
remember has the status like קונם konam, *Konam*, right? It's like קרבן
*Korban*. It means that the thing, you're changing the status of the
object, it's banned, it's forbidden, etc. So I am toward you חרם
cherem *Cherem*, meaning my objects are חרם cherem, *Cherem* as for you.
Yeah, well that's what you would think. And the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*
says המודר אסור hamudar assur, אבל מגדייר לו *Hamudar Assur Aval Magdir
Lo*. Now מודר mudar *Mudar* means, and these are terms we just
learned, talking about grammar, okay, because מודר mudar *Mudar* is the one
to whom the נדר neder *Neder* is directed. The מגדייר *Magdir* is
the one making the נדר neder, *Neder*. Could also be
נודר *Nodeir*. Okay, so so
so get your terms straight. This is S-Jacks, now we're talking grammar.
Interesting. I'm just my fruit. Okay, and there's you, and I'm telling
you you can't eat it. So you say מודרני
ממך mudrani mimcha, *Mudrani Mimcha* or something like that. Okay, so this
guy is the מגדייר *Magdir*. Pointing doesn't work.
This guy is the מגדייר *Magdir*,
alright. This guy is the מודר *Mudar*. Okay, or the נודר *Nodeir*.
This is the מגדייר *Magdir*, the נודר *Nodeir*, okay? So get your
terms straight.
Yeah. Okay, so if this guy says, all right, if this guy
says,
all right, הריני *Hareini*. is forbidden to eat my food. But the
מודר, me, the one speaking, well, I can eat your food. Now
the משנה mishna says, but how does that fit with what רבי
יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yossi bar Chanina said? Because why don't we
interpret that in both directions? You didn't say my food is חרם,
cherem you said I to you is חרם. cherem, So why don't
we interpret that in both directions? Okay, now, the משנה mishna goes
on to say something different, right? Because חרם cherem refers to the
status of an object. And therefore, it means my food is חרם,
cherem you know, as opposed to your food. Whereas the phrase that
רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yossi bar Chanina. was talking about, מודרני
ממך, mudrani mimcha is about the relationship. Right? As we learned, if
I say מודרני ממך, mudrani mimcha, I'm going to have nothing to
do with you. Okay, it goes back back to going in both
directions. I don't want to get benefit from you, you don't get
benefit from me, etc. If I say my stuff, you know, I
am a חרם cherem. or my stuff is a חרם, cherem then
that only refers to my stuff, not your stuff. So the גמרא
Gemara goes on and interprets it that way, and it assumes that
as long as there is some ambiguity here,
if I am a חרם cherem, to you, then also somehow you're
a חרם cherem to me, it's interpreted in both directions. Okay, so
how does this fit with what רבי יוסי בר
חנינא said? One minute. סיפא הריני לכם חרם והמודר אסור. seifa hareini
lachem cherem vehamudar assur. So how does that fit? It's just because
the משנה... Mishnah no, no, no, that's when you're more explicit and
you said, ואת עלי לא, ve'at alai lo, but you and I
are...
but you are not forbidden to me. One minute. So then it's
also pretty obvious. And it says, so let's go on with the
משנה. Mishnah. ואת עלי חרם, ve'at alai cherem, you are to me
חרם. cherem המודר אסור, assur,
so the one who made the נדר neder is forbidden because I'm
saying your stuff is חרם cherem to me. והמודר, vehamudar, you, the
one who I'm talking to, well, is not forbidden to get benefit
from my stuff. So why is that? When I say you are
to me חרם, cherem, why don't we interpret that to be like
about the relationship, you are חרם cherem to me, I am חרם
cherem, to you, and that goes in both directions? So the גמרא
Gemara says the same answer. It's because you also went and explicated
and you said, you are to me חרם cherem, ואני עליך לא,
ve'ani alecha lo,
but me to you no. All right, so of course then it's
all pretty obvious. And the גמרא Gemara says, אבל סתמא מאי? aval
stama mai? So what are you going to tell me? If we
don't have that explanation at the end,
שניהם אסורים, sheneihem asurim. are they both forbidden as that statement? How
can you say that? Because the end of the משנה says, הריני
עליך ואת עלי, hareini alecha ve'at alai, I am forbidden to you
and you to me, שניהם אסורים, they're both forbidden. So it's very
clear, I mean, it's really pretty clear from the beginning, right, that
if you say only the first half of the statement, it only
works in one direction. So the גמרא Gemara says, הדין דשניהם אסורים,
haden deshneihem assurim, it's in that case when they're both forbidden when
you explicitly say me and you and you and me. הא סתמא,
ha stama, but if it's just plain, הוא אסור, hu assur, if
you
just say you are to me חרם, cherem, הוא אסור, hu assur,
I can't take benefit from your stuff, וחברו מותר, vechavero mutar, but
you can benefit from my stuff. So why when you say הריני
עליך חרם or ואת עלי חרם ve'at alai cherem do you interpret
that only in one direction, but what רבי יוסי בר חנינא says,
מודרני ממך, mudrani mimcha, we interpret in both directions? So now again,
if you had asked me, because one חרם refers to the status
of the object, and מודרני ממך Mudrani mimcha refers more directly to
the relationship. But the גמרא Gemara does not say that. So the
גמרא Gemorah sees this as a real challenge for רבי יוסי בר
חנינא. So let's see what the גמרא Gemorah says. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אלא הכי אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא, ela hachi amar
Rabbi Yossi bar Chanina, here is what רבי יוסי... how רבי יוסי
בר חנינא says it: מודרני לך שניהם אסורים, mudrani lecha shneihem assurim,
מודרני ממך הוא אסור וחברו מותר. mudrani mimcha hu assur vechavero mutar.
If I say מודרני לך, mudrani lecha,
so I am מודר to you, then it works in both directions.
If I say I am מודר from you, then it takes the
meaning I am withholding my stuff from you, right? So my stuff
is forbidden, so let's first start with the ממך, mimcha from you.
If you say מודרני ממך, Mudrani mimcha, so I am withdrawing myself
from you and from your stuff, so הוא אסור וחברו מותר. hu
assur vechavero mutar. Then it only works in one direction. Your stuff
is forbidden to me, but you can benefit from my stuff. I
am withdrawing myself from you. So, wait, what? Why does the לך
l'cha? make it different? Wait, I said it the wrong way, haha.
ממך, mimcha I am withdrawn from your stuff, excuse me. So he
says, so he says... well we'll get to that in a minute.
Let's first figure out what he's saying. Okay, מודרני ממך, mudrani mimcha
so I say I am taking my stuff away from you and
from your stuff, so הוא אסור וחברו מותר. hu assur vechavero mutar.
Then it works in one direction. Your stuff is forbidden to me,
but you can benefit from my stuff. I am withdrawing myself from
you. So what
is... why does the לך l'cha? make it
different? So the
לך l'cha? somehow means
that
the... let's read the ר"ן Ran maybe on this instead of an
idol. Okay, let's... הכי איתמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Hachi itmar Rav
Yehudah Amar Shmuel מודרני לכו Mudrani lacho שניהם אסורים דלכו משמע לכו
Delacho mashma lacho כלומר נכסי אסורין לכו Kolomar nechasai asurin lacho so
my stuff is forbidden to you and משמע מיכו mashma micho from
your stuff. Okay. So, I don't know, that explains what
he says. Here it is: מודר אני לכו, Mudar ani licho, okay,
so one way to read it is, what is it saying?
Right, so מודר אני Mudar ani I am removing my stuff לכו,
licho, I don't know how לכו licho means... it means כלומר נכסי
אסורין לכו, kolomar nechasai asurin licho, so my stuff is forbidden to
you, not removed from you, but forbidden to you. Okay, so מודר
אני Mudar ani it's my stuff,
right, is forbidden to you, forbidden
to you. That's one way. My stuff is forbidden to you, that's
the לכו. licho. My stuff is forbidden to you. Okay, but it
could also be that I am
removing my
stuff, removing my stuff, maybe מישה לכו misha licho from your stuff.
So somehow the לכו licho because it doesn't have I guess you
know add like a
little prefix there can be read both ways. Okay, my stuff is
forbidden to you and removing myself from מישה לכו misha licho from
your stuff. Okay, so that's why it means both directions.
מודרני mudrani is both ways, but מודרני ממך mudrani mimcha from you
cannot be read in both directions. Okay, I am removing myself from
you מודרני, mudrani, right, this is from you, from which means from
your stuff. Okay,
so from your stuff. The ממך mimcha makes it very clear from
your stuff, so I am removing
myself from your stuff. There's no way you can read
ממך mimcha to
mean your
stuff is forbidden to me... no, my
stuff is forbidden to you. But לכו licho because it doesn't have
a prefix, right, this direction it's going, can be read both directions.
My stuff is forbidden to you, I'm removing myself, then you add
a prefix, from your stuff. So the difference is very clear which
direction it's going in. Okay, I am taking myself away, right, I
am removing myself away from you.
All right, so that's the answer. Can't get too excited about it.
But let's look in the גמרא Gemara again. So המשנה hamishnah says
like this, one minute. אלא הכי איתמר רב יוסף בר חנינא Ela
hachi itmar Rav Yosef bar Chanina מודר אני לכו Mudrani licho שניהם
אסורים.
I am either you know forbidding myself to you or removing myself
from you, even though לכו licho means to, but you can make
it מישה misha from לכו, licho, then that works in both directions.
מודרני הימך,
I am removing myself from your stuff, ממך mimcha from your stuff,
הוא אסור וחברו מותר hu asur vechaveiro mutar when I am forbidden
on your stuff,
but not in the opposite direction. Let's just get through this idea
and then I'll take your question. Okay, so that explains how רב
יוסף בר חנינא Rav Yosef bar Chanina is not contradicting the way
the משנה goes. He's saying a special case of לכו. licho. But
if he's saying a special case of לכו, licho, it goes back
to the question of what was שמואל Shmuel saying? Because remember שמואל
Shmuel said מודר אני ממך שאני אוכל לך. Mudar ani mimcha sheani
ochel lacho. And שמואל says you need both parts of the statement.
And the question was well why? So we said oh, because we
just said this it was going in both directions. But now we're
saying that's not true. ממך only goes in one direction. Both directions
only when you say לכו. licho. ממך already only goes in one
direction. So we're back to the question of what was שמואל saying?
So the גמרא Gemara.
says all right, you know what,
let's go back and say שמואל meant something else. אלא מעתה דשמואל
הכי איתמר. Ela meata deShmuel hachi itmar. This is what שמואל said.
טעמא דאמר שאני אוכל לך ושאני טועם לך Teima deamar sheani ochel
lacho vesheani toeim lacho הוא דאין אסור אלא באכילה. hu deein asur
ela bachilah. That if you say both phrases, מודרני ממך, mudrani mimcha,
it goes in one direction, I'm removing myself from you from your
stuff, now what am I saying about your stuff? That I
won't eat... that the stuff of yours that I won't eat I'm
removing myself, which means your stuff is forbidden for me to eat,
right, that's what I'm saying. Okay, so if I say that I
won't eat the stuff of yours that I won't. But now what
we're going to find out is, let's say I make my stuff
forbidden. What can't I do with it, right? Can I, can I
scratch my back with it? Can I sit on it? Can I
eat it, right? Can I not eat it? Can I not derive
any sort of, how do you define the parameters of when I
do make my stuff forbidden to you or your stuff forbidden to
me, what ways can I, can I not derive benefit? What is,
is it אסור בהנאה, assur b'hana'ah, אסור באכילה? assur b'achilah? So Shmuel
says if you say the phrase שאיני אוכל לך ושאיני טועם לך,
she'ani ochel lach v'she'ani toeim lach, you're saying that the status that
it's changing it into is איסור אכילה, issur achilah, because טעימה te'imah
is also a type of אכילה, achilah, to taste. Okay? But if
you didn't say this, if you just said I am removed from
your stuff, your stuff is forbidden to me, it would be more
generic. It would be even אסור בהנאה, assur b'hana'ah, any benefit. So
let's read in and let's take common. So, תלמוד לומר שאיני אוכל
לך ושאיני טועם לך, Talmud lomar she'ani ochel lach v'she'ani toeim lach,
I am removing myself from your stuff and your stuff is forbidden
to me in the context of eating and tasting. In that case,
אין הוא אסור אלא באכילה באכילה, ein hu assur ela b'achilah b'achilah,
the, the, it's only forbidden to me to be eaten but not
other benefit. מדרני ממך, Mudrani mimcha, if I just say that I
am removing myself from your stuff, your stuff is forbidden to me
without any qualifiers, אסור אכילה והנאה, assur achilah v'hana'ah, you can't even
derive benefit. Okay, so that seems to be a more, it's a
simple understanding of Shmuel. שאיני אוכל לך She'ani ochel lach makes it
specific. What is the scope of that איסור? issur? Without this qualifier,
it is, it is, you know, unlimited. Now Michael, you were starting
to ask a question. This just answers what I was saying, but
I would have thought that if you just looked at it simply,
מדרני ממך mudrani mimcha means just that, from you. To me, I
can't benefit in any single way, shape, or form. Scratch my back,
sit on it, use the chair, מדרני ממך. mudrani mimcha. Right, so
we're about to get to that. So that's coming up. Okay, did
you have a question? Okay, yes. Right, so usually the גמרא Gemara,
works all this out together as a logic that not only is
הכי hachi but also works through. But as we'll see, as any
of this, any of the explanation given is just a פסיקא psika
on, right, right, right. Like why is the גמרא gemara doing this
for the ages? Right, yeah, question, right, in general, why are they
doing it for the ages? Right. So let me say, let me
point out something. This is or not a long one, but this
is a classic opening סוגיא, sugya, right, of the גמרא. Gemara Now
it is true you have an אמר שמואל, okay, so I can't
say we're still just in the opening סוגיא. sugya. But if you
think about it, right, you know, we, we have had like, it's
all been very, very, you know, sort of, you know, expository, it
hasn't, I mean maybe less so here because it does start with
a statement of Shmuel and trying to figure out those parameters. But
I understand your frustration. You're not dealing with like a lot of
hard data and trying to be very concrete and specific about, you
know, what's, what's, like הלבשה halbasha or whatever. Right, but what, how
can I translate this to, to you know, in the other, as
a time period of like... right, so that's the point of... yeah,
but it's not just terminology, it is getting at some basic principles.
Okay, we're about to get, we're about to turn to a more
conceptual principle discussion. So you're right. Until now, I completely agree with
you, but let's hold, hold on. We're going to turn the page
and then it's going to start feeling like a more classic סוגיא,
sugya, at least to some degree. Okay, so משה Moshe says like
this. Okay, so that's one. You have to be specific. If you're
generic, it means אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah. Now that is an important
principle. If you just say something is forbidden, חרם, נדר, neder קונם,
without saying in what way, we're going to assume it means איסור
הנאה issur hana'ah unless you are more limiting and specific and say
regarding אכילה achilah or specific. Let's read a little more. So it
says, אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah. אי הכי, Ei hachi, says the גמרא,
Gemara נימא שמואל הכי. neima Shmuel hachi. What am I saying? We
learn the following: ואי לא אמר אלא שאיני אוכל לך ושאיני טועם
לך, ve'i lo amar ela she'ani ochel lach v'she'ani toeim lach, אין
אסור אלא באכילה. ein assur ela b'achilah. If you, if you, if
you don't say, but if you say שאיני אוכל לך, she'ani ochel
lach, that's when it's אסור, assur that's when it's only אסור באכילה.
assur b'achilah. Meaning when Shmuel says, like, if you, it's not enough
to say מדרני ממך mudrani mimcha alone. You have to also say
שאיני אוכל לך. she'ani ochel lach. That sounds like if you say
מדרני ממך mudrani mimcha alone, it's not אסור assur at all. Like
that was Shmuel's statement. It's not enough to say מדרני ממך. mudrani
mimcha. You have to say שאיני אוכל לך. she'ani ochel lach. That
sounds like this by itself doesn't do anything. But what we're saying
is the opposite. If you say מדרני ממך, mudrani mimcha, it's too
broad. Okay? And if you want to limit it, you have to
say שאיני אוכל לך. she'ani ochel lach. Okay? So the way Shmuel
articulated it is again, it's bit ironic because we're talking about how
exactly he articulated it when, when, אלא פסק. ela psak. But the
way Shmuel articulated it does not sound like that. אלא פסק. ela
psak. Let's try this way. הכי איתמר. hachi itmar. טעמא דאמר ta'ama
de'amar שיהא לו חלב she-yehei lo chalav ושיטעם לי v'shiteim li הוא
דאסור. If you say that I want it to have a taste,
that's when it's forbidden. אבל אמר מודרני ממך, aval amar mudrani mimcha,
if you just say generic I'm forbidden from you, so the first
thing meant all your stuff is forbidden unqualified בהנאה. be'hana'ah. Here we're
going to say who knows in what way what way you even
meant to say I'm removing myself from you or you're forbidden to
me. ומשמע דאמר אסור, u'mashma de'amar assur, maybe you're not saying that
all your stuff is forbidden to me, right? I didn't say שאני
אוכל לך. she'ani ochel lach. I was not clear as to what
I was talking about. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama why? Maybe it means
the following: מודרני ממך mudrani mimcha, לא שיינא בהדך. lo sheina behadach.
If I'm saying that I am removing myself from you, maybe I
don't want to talk to you. Okay? משמע mashma משום שאני מופרש
ממך mishum she'ani mufrash mimcha שלא אוביל ממך משא ומתן, shelo ovil
mimcha masa u'matan, I'm not doing business with you. Okay what's it?
I've had enough of you, I'm done with you. משמע mashma מרוחק
אני ממך, meruchak ani mimcha, I'm keeping my distance from you שלא
אעמוד בארבע אמותיך. shelo amod b'arba amotecha. I won't stand in your
four cubits. I don't know if you noticed that almost all these
things are aspects of חרם, including something in חרם, right? Not to
stand in your four cubits, not to do משא ומתן, masa u'matan,
not to talk to them. Okay but all these are ways in
which you separate from somebody. So what's it saying that the משנה
says מודרני ממך mudrani mimcha does not mean anything by itself. You
need to say שאני אוכל לך. she'ani ochel lach. But מודרני ממך,
mudrani mimcha מודרני מאי ממך, mai mimcha, who knows you mean נדר
neder and you're אסרing ossar an object? Maybe you're just saying that's
it I'm done I you know you I'm I'm I'm separating myself
from you. But how do you know you're talking about an איסור
חפצא issur cheftza and a נדר neder and a נדר neder as
opposed to just making a distance from yourself? If you say מודרני,
if you say מודרני ממך, mudarni mimcha you didn't do anything. What
did you say? שאני אוכל לך? she'ani ochel lach? I won't talk
with you. Yeah. So that's the question that the משנה asks. Is
it according to that idea that מודרני ממך mudarni mimcha might mean
I won't talk with you, it doesn't create a נדר neder? that
you won't talk to you? And no, so there's a מחלוקת ראשונים.
machlokes rishonim. The general assumption based on the next line that we're
going to see in the גמרא Gemara is it doesn't do anything.
Why doesn't it do anything? For one of two reasons. Either because
since it is so ambiguous it doesn't mean anything. If something has
no clear meaning, then you can't give it a meaning. So מודרני
ממך could mean I don't want to talk to you and it
could mean and it could mean your stuff is forbidden for me
to be eaten, could mean, so who knows? So we assume it
doesn't mean anything. It means nothing. Completely nothing. No, it means nothing.
Completely nothing. Okay I'm not gonna but that's then when you say
contradictory things I'm not gonna get into that. So basically if you
say something and its meaning is just way too open, then it
can't have any halachic meaning and that's part of the idea that
we've been talking about that נדר neder. needs to be through an
idea of יד yad. and there's an idea of כינוי kinuy and
so on, but you need to speak צח, tzach, you need to
say something that has some that has some type of a meaning.
So one understanding is it means nothing as if you mean two
various things it means nothing, and another understanding by the way also
is, is that to what degree, and here's something I want you
to think about, to what degree can you make something אסור בנדר
assur b'neder in those weird ways. Like let's say we spoke about
איסור אכילה issur achilah and איסור הנאה. issur hana'ah. איסור אכילה issur
achilah and איסור הנאה issur hana'ah are things that we are familiar
with, right, in terms of Torah statuses that something is אסור באכילה
assur b'achilah or אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah. Let's you know but there's
also like other things I could do. Let's say I wanted to
say this chair is אסור assur to me for sitting, right? Other
things I could do. This hat is אסור assur to me for
the purpose of putting it on my head. Okay? Is that a
נדר? neder Can you make something אסור assur in a very specific
way? Can I make you אסור assur to me like an איסור
חפצא, issur cheftza, remember it's a שבועה? shvua? I'm changing your status.
You now become the object and you're אסור assur to me regarding
talking. Okay? Or you're אסור assur to me regarding me standing in
your ארבע אמות. arba amos. Is that even use as an איסור
issur object and me standing in your ארבע אמות? arba amos? Like
that's not a הנאה hana'ah or it's a usage, is that a
work? So that's something I want you to think about because we'll
get to that. Like somebody could say this סוכה sukkah is אסור
assur to me to be sat in. This לולב lulav is אסור
assur to me to be taken. Okay? So but that's already interesting
phenomena and we will see phenomena like that but let's not take
that for granted. So that's one thing that about what I said,
I don't want to speak to you, is can you even create
an איסור חפצא issur cheftza of object being אסור or me being
the object in this particular way? That's one thing. Right and let's
say even if it was חל? chal? Right, you take משום, mishum,
you take נדר. neder So that's one thing. Right whether it's חל.
chal. Even if I explicitly said like קונם יומי עלי konam yumi
alai that I won't talk to you. Okay? Does that make sense?
Right? Is that an איסור חפצא? issur cheftza? How does that work?
Right? Exactly. Exactly. So okay, that's one thing about can it work?
But the other thing is even assuming it can work, if you
say this, we have no idea what you meant. We have no
idea what you meant. Did you mean your object is אסור בהנאה?
assur b'hana'ah? Did you mean... what you mean and you said nothing.
Only when you say "which I eat of yours," now I understand
what you mean. You have to specify in דכחמינא, de-chamana, and now
this gets to an important principle. Rava should have said it. Well,
well, that's he's reading the משנה that regarding he requires this. That's
his reading of the משנה. Okay. Okay. דכחמינא. de-chamana. So now it's
going to try to get—and now we get to a real classic
סוגיא sugya that discusses this principle: לימא קסבר שמואל, Leima kasavar Shmuel,
so let's say what שמואל holding is, ידיים שאינן מוכיחות לא הויין
ידיים. yadayim she-einan mochi-chot lo havyen yadayim. A hand, an elliptical statement
which is not clear what it means, is not a יד. yad,
Okay, so there are three stages of—of—of this idea of יד, yad
an elliptical statement. There's a יד מוכיח, yad mochi-ach, okay, where it's
very clear what you mean. Okay, an example would be like—here's an
example: you're under the חופה chuppah and you say—this happens—it happened to
me once—when you're under the חופה chuppah and you say—and the חתן
chosson says to the כלה, kallah, הרי את מקודשת, Harei at mekudeshet,
and he doesn't say לי. li. So who's she marrying? Anyway, this
happened once at a חופה chuppah and the—and the חתן chosson said
הרי את מקודשת Harei at mekudeshet and he didn't say לי. li.
I was the מסדר. mesader. So afterwards, I went up to the
עדים eidus and I said, did he say לי? li? and they
said I don't know, I thought he did, like how? So anyway,
so then afterwards I went—I said to the חתן chosson and I
said, I don't think you said לי. li. He said you're crazy,
of course I did! Anyway, so three months later I get a
phone call, why is my get from Cincinnati? Anyway, it was fine
because it was a יד מוכיח yad mochi-ach because they were under
the חופה. chuppah. Okay, but okay, so that's a case where you
didn't say it but it's מוכיח. mochi-ach. Now, if you were—because there's
context, right? Now, or like, or you could just say, now maybe
it's—now maybe sometimes it's just clear even without context because like of
course that's what—of course that's what the missing part of the sentence
was, right? So—so even if you don't need any context to fill
in the blanks, you can fill in the blanks yourself. Okay, so
that's one thing. Now there's a יד שאינה מוכיח, yad she-einah mochi-ach,
which means that let's say you weren't under the חופה. chuppah. Okay,
so הרי את מקודשת, Harei at mekudeshet, you know, it's most likely
he meant לי, li, but there's a possibility if you live in
a time when people send a שליח shaliach to go ahead and
marry women, right, אברהם Avraham sent his servant, whatever, you know, to
marry רבקה, Rivka, so he might have said הרי את מקודשת Harei
at mekudeshet and he didn't mean לי, li, he meant ליצחק. le-Yitzchak.
So in that type of a way, most likely we know it
was לי, li, but it's not 100% clear. That's a יד שאינה
מוכיח. yad she-einah mochi-ach. Okay. And then there are cases where it's
not even a יד yad at all, like you know, the sentence
means nothing, like you know, I am, you know, I am what?
You know, who knows? So that's not just a יד שאינה מוכיח,
yad she-einah mochi-ach, that's not even a יד yad at all. So
there's three different degrees, okay? So what the גמרא Gemara assumes is
מודרני ממך is a יד שאינה מוכיח, yad she-einah mochi-ach, which means
most likely you do not mean I'm not talking with you. In
a world where נדר neder. means נדר neder and refers to making
objects forbidden, מודרני ממך most likely probably means your food is forbidden
to me. But because it might not mean that, it might mean
I don't want to talk to you, okay, so therefore שמואל says
it's not a binding statement. So that's the principle of ידיים שאינן
מוכיחות לא הויין ידיים. yadayim she-einan mochi-chot lo havyen yadayim. If it's
not clear what you mean, if there's some ambiguity about what you
mean, then it is not a יד yad, and the statement means
nothing and it is not a speech act. Okay, so now we're
really getting into the fine—of this idea of speech acts, that something
can have two possible meanings, one is the more likely one, one
less likely, that's a יד שאינה מוכיח. yad she-einah mochi-ach. It's pretty
clear but there's ambiguity. Is that still considered a speech act or
because of that ambiguity it doesn't mean anything? ידיים שאינן מוכיחות לא
הויין ידיים. yadayim she-einan mochi-chot lo havyen yadayim. So whatever you want
to say. In the case of the marriage, if there's two people
who are unmarried within earshot and you didn't say את, at, oh,
you didn't say את. at. Okay, so anyway, if you don't say
את at anyway, maybe she was a שליח shaliach for another woman.
Oh that's true. Anyway, alright, so, so yes, so, if it's not
a speech act, it's just sound. Not a speech act, it's just
trying to get to your דעת, da'at, so it might have different
criteria. Okay, but the idea of יד מוכיח yad mochi-ach is—well we'll
see after, right? Is that a question about how we assess your
דעת? da'at? It could be, but I'd rather say for our purposes
we're going to assume that it's not a question of assessing דעת,
da'at, it's a question of what constitutes as a speech act. So
we might be prepared to say, you know what, if I were
to question... of what you were thinking I have no doubt that
what you were thinking was that you wanted the food to be
forbidden but the words you said didn't say that. The words you
said could have reasonably have been interpreted otherwise and therefore it wasn't
a statement. So that's again important to remember that the focus here
is not דעת, da'as, the focus here is does that constitute the
act of speech? If if there is some ambiguity to that statement?
Okay so it was like this: לימא קסבר שמואל ידיים שאינן מוכיחות
לא הויין ידיים. Leima kasavar Shmuel yadayim she'einan mochiachot lo havyan yadayim.
So maybe that's what Shmuel's whole thing is? So Gemara says: אין,
In, yes, שמואל מוקים לה מתניתין כרבי יהודה, Shmuel mokim lah matnitin
k'Rabbi Yehuda, דאמר ידיים שאינן מוכיחות לא הויין ידיים, d'amar yadayim she'einan
mochiachot lo havyan yadayim, that a handle which is not clear, a
statement with some ambiguity is not is not is not a statement,
okay, if it's not exactly clear what the end of that statement
is. Okay, דתנן, d'tnan, as we taught in a Mishna: גופו של
גט, Gufo shel get, what is the text of a get that
you write in a get? הרי את מותרת לכל אדם, Harei at
muteset l'chol adam, behold you are permitted to every person. You're permitted,
you're permitted to every person. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, Rabbi
Yehuda says no no no, you have to add the following line:
ודן דיהוי ליכי מינאי ספר תירוכין ואגרת שבוקין, V'den d'yehevei lichi minai
sefer tiruchin v'igeret shivukin, this, ודן, v'den, ודן דיהוי ליכי מינאי, v'den
d'yehevei lichi minai, to you from me, ספר תירוכין, sefer tiruchin, a
book of divorce, a writ of divorce, דיהוי ליכי מינאי, d'yehevei lichi
minai, ואגרת שבוקין, v'igeret shivukin, and a writ of release. Okay now,
so what does that prove that ידיים שאינן מוכיחות? yadayim she'einan mochiachot?
So the Gemara says, okay, that, I mean there's different ways of
explaining this, but simply that when I say behold you are הרי
את מותרת לכל אדם, Harei at muteset l'chol adam, I am not
necessarily saying that I am divorcing you with this get. I'm just
making a declaration in this get. So I hand you this thing
that says הרי את מותרת לכל אדם, Harei at muteset l'chol adam,
maybe is it clear that I understand that this is the instrument
of divorce? Maybe I just think that I've declared that you're divorced
and I'm just giving you know you know giving you my statement
in writing. You know, but how do we know that I am
indicating that this is the writ that is effecting the divorce? So
Rabbi Yehuda says you have to say that explicitly: ודן, V'den, this,
this writ, this document, shall be the writ of divorce. Okay, is
that clear? Otherwise it's just a written statement. Behold you're I'm writing
down I'm telling you, I can tell you orally, I can tell
you in writing. Okay, but it doesn't show me that I see
this as the instrument that's effecting the divorce. So ודן v'den is
the ודן, v'den, right, so you can understand it's a little different
here because it's not a speech act. It's about defining what constitutes
a written instrument. But it is similar that it's not just a
question of your intention. Maybe this even makes it clearer the importance
of the speech act, right? No one cares how much a man
wants to divorce his wife. If you don't have the right type
of a written document that follows the right formula, it is not
an instrument of divorce. So similarly no one cares how much you
want to make the food forbidden. If you don't have the right
type of speech act, it's not going to become forbidden. So so
here, right, but it's the same idea that it requires a certain
type of words. So here, so here, so here, if you the
argument is if we assume now, of course the חכמים Chachamim could
say okay, but what's required in the written document does not have
to make it explicit how it's operating. But that's how the Gemara
is choosing to interpret it, that the argument part of what the
document requires is that it makes it clear not just that he's
expressing in terms of divorcing her, but it makes it clear that
this is the document of divorce. That's required as part of the
statement of the document. So the so Rabbi Yehuda says well that's
not implicit. Okay, and you have to make it implicit, and the
Gemara in choosing to
interpret it as a position that ידיים שאינן מוכיחות לא הויין ידיים.
yadayim she'einan mochiachot lo havyan yadayim. It's possible you mean something else
by those words, the words themselves are not identifying this as the
writ of divorce. Yes me too that is specifically too that's the
picture of no because the question is what what makes it a
book a writ that divorces? The חכמים Chachamim say that that in
that context I'm divorcing you. And Rabbi
Yehuda says no no no in order for it to
be a writ of
divorce it has to make it clear that that's its function.
So you're right you could say that the חכמים Chachamim are just
debating what the criteria is. Okay, but you could say and I
agree but the Gemara is
choosing to read
it that the חכמים Chachamim agree that that's
the criteria but they're saying that it's satisfied.
Yes we're agreeing that
the writ has to be clear that it is the instrument of
divorce but that's clear from context. Okay whereas
it's not clear from context it could mean something else. In theory
they could be debating the criteria but the Gemara is choosing to
say that they're agreeing what the nature of the of the script
has to not script of the text has to be and they're
just debating whether
or not you satisfied it and therefore it's a question of ידיים
שאינן מוכיחות. yadayim she'einan mochiachot. Yes Bobby. Okay, fine. So. Okay, so.
Okay, so the Gemara is but absolutely, we could have said that
this is a basic debate of what are the specific criteria of
the text of a גט, get, right? But the Gemara chooses to
say it's a debate about whether those criteria are satisfied. And they
say that the document has to make
it clear that this is the instrument of divorce, and Yehuda
says you have to say that explicitly, it's
not
implicit. Okay, so the Gemara says like this: אמאי דחיק שמואל לאוקמה
למתניתין כרבי יהודה? Amai dachik Shmuel l'ukma l'matnitin k'Rabbi Yehuda? Why did
Shmuel push to interpret our Mishnah like Rabbi Yehuda? Remember, if we
have the debate of ידיים שאין מוכיחות, yadayim she'ein mochichot, then if
you hold הוויין ידיים, havyan yadayim, it works by itself. Because if
there's some ambiguity, it's pretty clear what you mean, and that works
by itself. To say you need the second part, by this itself
it does nothing, that means לא הוויין ידיים. lo havyan yadayim. And
you'll remember the Gemara quoted a ברייתא baraita that said explicitly that
הוויין ידיים, havyan yadayim, it works by itself. So the Gemara is
saying, look, there's a debate of ידיים שאין מוכיחות, yadayim she'ein mochichot,
which is essentially going to be a debate whether הוויין ידיים havyan
yadayim works by itself. We have ברייתות baraitot that say הוויין ידיים,
havyan yadayim, which means הוויין ידיים. havyan yadayim. Why did Shmuel choose
to interpret our מתניתין matnitin according
to the דעת יחיד da'at yachid of Rabbi Yehuda
that לא הוויין ידיים, lo havyan yadayim, and it means nothing until
you have the second part of the statement? Right? Why
did he choose to take that approach rather than the approach which
says הוויין ידיים? havyan yadayim? Okay, well, that's what the Gemara asks.
I mean, you know, there are other places where Shmuel פסקס paskens
like Rabbi Yehuda. But anyway, fine, of
course there's motivation to פסקן pasken like Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, so ואמאי
דחיק שמואל לאוקמה למתניתין כרבי יהודה? V'amai dachik Shmuel l'ukma l'matnitin k'Rabbi
Yehuda? נוקמה כרבנן? Nokma k'rabbanan? Why not
interpret it like the Rabbis? אף על גב דאין ידיים מוכיחות, Af
al gav de'ein yadayim mochichot, but even though it's not, you know,
evident, so it's not, you know, even though there's some ambiguity, it
still works, and the first part of the statement works by itself.
אמר רבא מתניתין קשיא ליה, Amar Rava: Matnitin kashya lei, the language
of the Mishnah troubled him. אמאי תני שמה שאני אוכל לך שאני
טועם לך? Amai tani shema 'she'ani ochel l'cha, she'ani to'em l'cha'? וליתני
שאני אוכל שאני טועם? V'litni 'she'ani ochel, she'ani to'em'? Why does it
say לך? l'cha Why don't you just say that I'll eat, you
know, regarding things that I'll eat or things that I'll taste? שמע
מינה בעינן ידיים מוכיחות. Shema mina: be'inan yadayim mochichot. Why would it
say לך? l'cha It's very clear. I'm talking to you. I am
separated from this, you know, ממך from you, regarding things that I
will eat, regarding things that I will taste. Right? Why do I
have to say לך? l'cha,
I'm talking to you. So the only reason it would say לך
is to tell me, hint
to
you, things have to
be very clear when you make a נדר. neder So you can't
allow for any ambiguity. Okay, so in the very text of the
Mishnah itself, the word לך is superfluous. And the only
reason you need to say לך, because the context
is
clear, is to signal that we actually demand clarity and,
you know, things to be very, you know, unambiguous. Alright, so that's
the view. The bottom line is he's saying that if there's some
ambiguity, even though it's pretty clear what you meant, it
does not count as a speech act, ידיים שאין מוכיחות לא הוויין
ידיים. yadayim she'ein mochichot lo havyan yadayim. Okay, now the Gemara says
like this: איתמר. Itmar. Now we're going to talk about that debate
directly. ידיים שאין מוכיחות, Yadayim she'ein mochichot, we have this issue about
handles of abbreviated statements that are not completely clear. אביי אמר הוויין
ידיים, Abaye amar: havyan yadayim, it counts, and it counts as a
speech act. ורבא אמר לא הוויין ידיים, v'Rava amar: lo havyan yadayim,
it's no, if there's some ambiguity it doesn't count. אמר רבא ובי
איבי אסברא לי, Amar Rava: v'Bi Ibi asbara li, ורב איבי v'Rav
Ibi explained to me why I should say that it doesn't work.
אמר קרא, Amar kara, this says, נזיר להזיר לה'. Nazir l'hazir l'Hashem.
And you remember we learned from להזיר l'hazir the idea of יד,
yad
right? It's pointing to נזירות nezirut even though
it's not explicit. מקיש ידי נזירות לנזירות. Makish yadei nezirut l'nezirut. And
it says, therefore, it links the idea of יד yad to נזירות
nezirut itself. מה נזירות בהפלאה אף ידי נזירות בהפלאה. Ma nezirut b'hafla'ah,
af yadei nezirut b'hafla'ah. The same way נזירות nezirut requires הפלאה, hafla'ah,
יד yad. requires הפלאה. hafla'ah. Now what's הפלאה hafla'ah mean? So הפלאה
hafla'ah basically means to articulate, as I said before, הפלאה hafla'ah becomes
a technical term which means things that are created through speech acts.
Okay, but the word להפלי l'hafli basically means to articulate.
And
articulating
means to be very concrete and very clear. So what does it
mean that נזירות nezirut requires הפלאה? hafla'ah? So the Gemara has a
debate between if somebody says, הריני נזיר אם זה נזיר, hareini nazir
im zeh nazir, somebody is walking in front of me and I
say הריני נזיר אם זה נזיר, hareini nazir im zeh nazir, I'll
be a נזיר nazir if this guy's a נזיר. nazir. Okay, and
then tomorrow we find out if he was a נזיר. nazir. So
what do you think? ספק אסור? safek assur? Okay, so you're a
נזיר. nazir. But there's an opinion that says, look, because it says
it requires הפלאה, hafla'ah, and הפלאה hafla'ah means that it has to
be very clear at the moment that it was uttered, okay, and
if at the moment it was uttered there was some ambiguity whether
it was taking effect, even if that was just an ambiguity out
of ignorance because you didn't know all the facts, nevertheless that's not
enough to be considered an act of נזירות. nezirut. Okay, now that
actually is a matter of some debate, but nevertheless the point is
that the concept of the word יפלי yafli means
that things have to be very... So therefore, if that's required that
things be very clear whether they're being effective or not, if that's
true about whether the act has taken effect is effective, it also
then becomes a criteria about the יד. yad For a יד yad
to work, it has to
be unambiguous. It's not enough of a הפלאה, haflaa, right? Of... of
this act of הפלאה. haflaa. Yeah, go ahead. But does one need
to say, so because you see it by נזיר nazir would it
apply across...? Yeah, but then we're going
to reject that because we learn יד yad of נדר from נזיר.
nazir.
So נזיר nazir tells
us things have to be unambiguous, from that
we apply it to the יד yad of נזיר, nazir, which tells
us that the יד yad has to be unambiguous, and then we
say that יד of נדר is also unambiguous. Yes?
I just want to make one observation. בישעיהו Be'Yeshayahu you've got
a cluster of the terms פלאים, pela'im, אותות, otot, and מופתים. moftim.
Those are all semiotic. And you've got like the הפלא
ופלא hafleh va-feleh which means to baffle, to... right. Which is really
interesting, right? Because those signs are actually
pointing to something with a specific meaning as it were. That type
of... you have a cluster there. Interesting. יישר כוח. Yasher koach. Alright,
also sounds semiotic. No, okay, anyway, so the גמרא says like this.
מאן דאמר הפלאה יד נדרים בעינן הפלאה. Man de-amar haflaa yad nedarim
be'inan haflaa. לימא כתנאי כדאמר רבי יהודה ורבנן כדאמרינן לעיל.
Leima ke-tanna'ei ke-de-amar Rabbi Yehuda
ve-Rabbanan ke-de-amrinan le-eil. So now the גמרא says, okay now we've set
out our camps, רבא ואביי דאמרי לה הכי ודאמרי לה הכי, Rava
ve-Abaye de-amri lah hachi ve-de-amri lah hachi, and now we're going
to say what we said before.
Is this or is this
not
the debate of this issue about what the text of the גט
get has to say? One minute. דתנן גופו של גט הרי את
מותרת לכל אדם. De-tenan gufo shel get harei at muteret le-khol adam.
רבי יהודה אומר ודן די יהוי ליכי מינאי ספר תירוכין ואגרת שבוקין
וגט פטורין. Rabbi Yehuda omer ve-dein de-yehei likhi minai sefer teirukhin ve-iggeret
shevukin ve-get pitturin. Okay, I skipped I think before the word גט
פטורין. get pitturin. Anyway, but means basically the same. אביי דאמר כרבנן,
Abaye de-amar ke-Rabbanan, ורבא דאמר כרבי יהודה. ve-Rava de-amar ke-Rabbi Yehuda. So
אביי Abaye says like the רבנן, Rabbanan, you don't have to spell
that out because a יד אינה מוכיחה yad einah mokhicha that's fine.
And רבא Rava says like רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda,
it's not
unambiguous and therefore
you have to spell it out. ואמר לך אביי,
Ve-amar lakh Abaye,
אביי Abaye will say to you, and I might be guessing here
your point, like no, come on, those things could be based on
some other debate. אנא דאמרי אפילו כרבי יהודה. Ana de-amri afilu ke-Rabbi
Yehuda. I could say even like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. I could
normally... יד אינה מוכיחה yad einah mokhicha is fine. So why does
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda have to spell it out? עד כאן לא
קאמר רבי יהודה בעינן ידיים מוכיחות. Ad kan lo ka-amar Rabbi Yehuda
be'inan yadayim mokhichot. Why does רבי
יהודה
Rabbi
Yehuda
require it to be spelled out explicitly by the גט? get? אלא
לגבי גט דבעינן כריתות. Ela legabi get de-be'inan kritut. Like Michael's point,
you know, maybe there's a higher criteria by גט, get, כריתות kritut
to sever the relationship, to totally cut it off means you don't
need any... any little string left. You don't need any doubts. It
has to be very clear, unambiguous, black and white. So
there you have to spell it out completely. אבל בעלמא, Aval be-alma,
the normal demand of what you need for a speech act, מי
סברת בעינן Mi savrat be'inan who says you need it to be
a hundred percent clear? כריתות
Kritut
of course has to be completely a hundred percent clear. ורבא אמר,
Ve-Rava amar, one minute, so that's why it's possible that רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda does require it explicit by גט, get, but he
would not
require things explicit by elsewhere. ורבא אמר אנא דאמרי אפילו כרבנן. Ve-Rava
amar ana de-amri afilu ke-Rabbanan. I could say even like the רבנן,
Rabbanan, that don't require things to be so explicit. עד כאן לא
קאמרי רבנן דלא בעינן ידיים מוכיחות. Ad kan lo ka-amri Rabbanan de-lo
be'inan yadayim mokhichot. Why do the רבנן Rabbanan say it
does not have to be evident over there by the גט? get?
אלא לגבי גט דאין אדם מגרש את אשת חבירו,
Ela legabi get de-ein
adam megaresh et eshet chaveiro, because there's... it's unambiguous. It's very unambiguous.
Who else are you divorcing? אבל בעלמא מי שמעת להו, Aval be-alma
mi sham'at le-hu, now where else do you get it from? Now,
one minute. Two things. First of all, the fact that it says
it is unambiguous because who else are you divorcing makes it sound
that the issue at stake with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda statement was...
was the question of... of who was being divorced. Not the way
I was saying before. I was saying before actually, you know, the
רמב"ן Ramban points out that both issues are at stake. One is
what's divorcing her? Am I divorcing her through this writ, this written
instrument of divorce, or am I just making a declaration? So that's
the importance of saying the first part of the statement, ודן די
יהוי ליכי מינאי, ve-dein de-yehei likhi minai, ודן די יהוי, ve-dein de-yehei,
this shall be, this document is the instrument. But there's another part
of the statement. If I just say הרי את מותרת לכל אדם,
harei at muteret le-khol adam, who am I talking to? Well, you
know, you know, it's not clear. Maybe I'm talking to somebody else.
But if I say ודן די יהוי ליכי מינאי, ve-dein de-yehei likhi
minai, this is to you, from me, it's clear. Well, right. So
that's basically, I have
to admit, I don't really understand why ליכי מינאי likhi minai is
any clearer than את. at. את at am
I giving it to her? Anyway, it seems that there's some question
of is it clear who
I'm talking
to. Maybe this woman is a שליח shaliach or something, I don't
know. Anyway, so therefore, that's what the גמרא seems to be pointing
out here. That if your concern was, you know, maybe you're talking
about someone else... No. It's like it's also saying me under the
חופה *chuppah*. There's no real question here who he's talking to. So
then the רבנן *Rabbanan* don't demand, and this is I think back
also when the רבנן *Rabbanan* say you don't have to spell it
all out here, it doesn't mean that they
don't
need something to be
a יד מוכיח *yad mochiach*. Maybe they do
need something to
be a יד מוכיח *yad mochiach*. They just say you have יד
מוכיח *yad mochiach* here. The context makes it very clear. The context
makes it clear that this is the instrument of divorce, the context
makes it clear that I'm divorcing my wife, who else am I
divorcing? Okay? Oh, it's—excuse me, it's not—it's who is the woman being
divorced, of course it's the woman in front of me, I already
said את *at*. The question is who's the man doing the divorcing?
If I just say הרי את מקודשת לכל אדם *harei at mikoodeshet
lechol adam*, it's not clear that I'm the one doing the divorcing,
maybe I'm a שליח *shaliach*, maybe I'm divorcing her from some other
man. Okay, of course, of course she's only married to you, which
is what the גמרא *Gemara* says: אין אדם מגרש אשת חבירו *ein
adam megaresh ishat chaveiro*, okay? You know,
but you have
to know you're divorcing from me. So anyway, the point is, the
response is, you know why
you don't have to make it explicit here? Not because ambiguity is
okay, but because there's no ambiguity! Of course you're divorcing your wife,
who else is divorcing, who else is being divorced, and of course
it's through this instrument. So basically רבא *Rava* would say: Look, in
general everybody says that ידים שאינם מוכיחות *yadayim she'einam mochiachot* doesn't work,
things need to be explicit. The only thing is context can also
work, and the רבנן *Rabbanan* here are saying it's okay, not because
they don't need it to be explicit, but because it is explicit.
Context makes it clear, and that's why it's
okay. So again, to recap, אביי *Abaye* says: Generally ambiguity, a
little ambiguity is fine, what's life without a little ambiguity? Okay, but
he says רבא *Rava* goes like—except for ספר כריתות *sefer krisus*, a
גט *get*, that's where רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* was
saying it's got
to be black and white. But otherwise a little ambiguity is fine.
And רבא *Rava* says: No, actually a little ambiguity
is not fine, things don't work if
they're not black and white. But in the case of a גט
*get* you don't have to spell it all out. You don't
have to spell it all out, it's still clear from context and
there's no ambiguity. And therefore they're both able to
say whatever's going on by גט *get*, they're still holding their two
basic camps in other areas. One other point I want to take
a question. The רן *Ran* points out: what does the גמרא *Gemara*
mean when it says at the bottom of ה עמוד ב *hay
amud bais*: עד כאן לא קא פלגי רבנן דבידים מוכיחות *Ad kan
lo ka’palgei Rabbanan de-be-yadayim mochiachot*. The רבנן *Rabbanan* say you don't need
ידים מוכיחות *yadayim mochiachot* by גט *get*. Okay, so that's—that's not
what we're saying. We're saying that they do need ידים מוכיחות *yadayim
mochiachot*, but you have it, right, because the context provides it. Right,
isn't that what we just said? You do need it
to be explicit, but the context provides
it. So why does the גמרא *Gemara* say they don't require it
to be explicit? They do require it to be explicit,
they're just saying that the context provides it. Is the question clear?
So the רן *Ran* says: No, here's the difference. There what's מוכיח
*mochiach* in the case by גט *get*
is not the יד *yad*. What's מוכיח *mochiach* is
the context. Okay, so it's an interesting conceptual distinction. Does the statement
itself, clear of any context, clear what it means? That's יד מוכיח
*yad mochiach*. Is the statement like when the person says הרי את
מקודשת *harei at mikoodeshet* without saying לי *li*, that's יד שאינו מוכיח
*yad she'eino mochiach*, because maybe he means 'I'm a שליח *shaliach*.' But
this guy, in his context, under the חופה *chuppah*, with the woman
in her wedding gown, does this become a יד מוכיח *yad mochiach*
or is this a יד שאינו מוכיח *yad she'eino mochiach* but the
context was מוכיח *mochiach*? Okay, either way it'll work, but that's an
interesting—that's the point that the רן *Ran* says. In this case, the
language is still a יד שאינו מוכיח *yad she'eino mochiach*, but it
works because the context is מוכיח *mochiach*. Alright. Bottom line is in
general you call ידים מוכיחות *yadayim mochiachot* through context, it winds up
being the same thing. Okay, but those are basically the issues when
you have either intrinsically or by context everybody agrees it works, that's
why the guy didn't have to redo the קידושין *kiddushin* when he
forgot to say לי *li*, but the question is when even with
context it's not clear and there's some ambiguity, and what it's most
likely we know what he means but as long as there's still
some ambiguity that's the debate of אביי *Abaye* and רבא *Rava*. Okay,
well, I'm just going to—Lenny
you had a question before I just want to finish that—yeah.